Robert Emmett Bledsoe Baylor papers, Inclusive: 1812-1981, undated, Bulk: 1837-1873
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Robert Emmett Bledsoe Baylor papers
Inclusive: 1812-1981, undated, Bulk: 1837-1873
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
1362
Baylor, Robert Emmett Bledsoe, 1793 - 1873
3 document boxes and 1 oversize folder.
The Robert Emmett Bledsoe Baylor papers are a collection of personal correspondence, legal documents, reminiscences, and biological entries concerning Judge Baylor. Most of the material deals with family issues and Baylor’s interactions with other Texas Baptists.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Robert Emmett Bledsoe Baylor, or R. E. B. Baylor, was born in Lincoln County, Kentucky, on 1793 May 10. His parents, Walker and Jane Bledsoe Baylor, had six children. Walker had served in the Continental Army as a member of the 3rd Light Dragoons. He was eventually promoted to captain and served as an orderly on General George Washington’s staff. Walker’s son Robert attended country schools for most of his adolescence. He was admitted to the bar in 1812, but postponed his legal career to fight in the War of 1812. As a member of the Kentucky Militia, Baylor participated in battles in Ohio Territory and in the ill-fated invasion of Canada.
After the end of the War of 1812, Baylor studied law with his uncle, Judge Jesse Bledsoe and became well-known throughout the area. In 1819, R.E.B. Baylor was elected to the Kentucky State Legislature. His reputation continued to grow after moving to Tuscaloosa, Alabama. In 1824, Baylor was elected to the Alabama State Legislature and became a United States Representative from that state in 1828. In 1836, Baylor led a battalion of Alabama volunteers against the Creek Indians.
One of the defining moments of R.E.B. Baylor’s life came in 1839 with his conversion to Christianity. He was ordained shortly after his conversion experience, leaving his flourishing political career in Alabama behind to spread the Gospel.
At the age of forty-six, Baylor moved to Texas where he continued to devote his life to law and his new faith. In 1841, he was appointed an associate justice of Texas’ Supreme Court. While judging cases around the state, he presided over the first district court held in Waco and preached perhaps the first sermon offered in Waco. He was involved in a number of religious organizations including the Texas Baptist Education Society, the Union Association, and the Texas Baptist State Convention. He had joined the Freemasons in 1825 and served as a chaplain for that society in 1843, 1846, and 1847.
Baylor was also instrumental in founding Baylor University, named for him when it was chartered in 1845. Despite his involvement as donor and law professor, Baylor was never a president of the school.
Although Baylor was never married nor had children, he was quite close to his nephew John Baylor, as John lived with him for a time and wrote to him often when he left Robert Baylor’s house. John Baylor led an adventurous life of his own as a noted Indian fighter, commander of the first Confederate invasion of New Mexico in the American Civil War, Confederate congressman, and gunfighter.
After a life of faith in God and public service to three states, Robert Baylor died on 1873 December 30. He was buried at Baylor University’s original campus in Independence, Texas, but his remains were transferred to the University of Mary-Hardin Baylor in 1917.
Scope and Content
The Robert Emmett Bledsoe Baylor papers are a collection of personal correspondence, legal documents, reminiscences, and biological entries concerning Judge Baylor. Most of the material deals with family issues and Baylor’s interactions with other Texas Baptists.
Much of the correspondence series is comprised of letters exchanged between Robert Baylor and his relatives: Walker Baylor (father), John Baylor (nephew), and an unnamed sister.
A large portion of the collection pertains to Joseph W. Hale who wrote a biography of Baylor entitled Baylor in Perspective. Hale’s correspondence, notes, and books are included in the collection.
Arrangement
Correspondence has been organized by individual when possible. The literary productions, particularly the biographical sketches of Baylor, have been organized by the author. Currently the records are arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, II. Legal Documents, and III. Literary Productions.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 1362. Acquired 1976-02-25
Related Resources
Items in related collections
Baylor-Carrington Family papers, Inclusive: 1715-2007, undated, Bulk: 1840-1930
Related references
Baker, Eugene W. In His Traces: The Life and Times of R.E.B. Baylor. Waco: Baylor University Press, 1996.
Murray, Lois S. Baylor at Independence: 1845-1886. Waco: Baylor University Press, 1998.
Summerlin, Travis L. “Robert Emmett Bledsoe Baylor.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 January 23.
Thompson, Jerry. “Baylor, John Robert.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2012 January 23.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Baylor, R. E. B. (Robert Emmett Bledsoe), 1793-1873.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History.
Subjects
Baptists -- Texas.; Land Deed -- Texas
Genres
Articles.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Legal documents.; Research notes.
- Correspondence, 1812-1951, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The correspondence series, the largest series in the collection, includes the correspondence of Baylor President R. E. B. Baylor as well as that of his biographer, Joseph Hale.
  - General, 1837-1851 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1853-1863 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General, 1868-1872 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, 1873, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - John Baylor, 1845-1856 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - John Baylor, 1857-1860 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - John Baylor, 1861-1868 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - R.E.B. Baylor’s Sister, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Walker Baylor, 1812-1822 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brother Stribling (1 of 2), 1871 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brother Stribling (2 of 2), 1871 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - James Huckins, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Masons, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Joseph W. Hale, 1944 October 16-24 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Joseph W. Hale, 1944 October 25-28 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Joseph W. Hale, 1944 November-December (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Joseph W. Hale, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Joseph W. Hale, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Joseph W. Hale (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Joseph W. Hale (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Legal Documents, 1836-1875; 2
  This series includes legal documents including land deeds, certificates, treasury warrants, and a declaration of pension.
  - General, 1836-1846 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - General, 1848-1859 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - General, 1860-1875 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Literary Productions, 1845-1981; 3
  The literary productions series contains reminiscences of Judge Baylor, but primarily consists of articles, essays, and books detailing the biographical details of Baylor’s life.
  - Article: Baptist Standard: Coleman Craig: “An Eminent Baptist and an Historic Occasion”, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Biographical Sketch: Dr. Henry W. Baylor, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Memorial: Masons, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notes: Joseph W. Hale, 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notes: Joseph W. Hale, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notes: Joseph W. Hale, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Essay: Herbert Gambrel: “Robert Emmett Bledsoe Baylor (1793-1873)”, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Essay: Samuel Hessler: “Robert Emmett Bledsoe Baylor”, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Essay: Joseph W. Hale: “Judge Baylor in Review”, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Essay: “Judge Baylor as a Man and Preacher”, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Reminiscences (1 of 4), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Reminiscences (2 of 4), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reminiscences (3 of 4), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Reminiscences (4 of 4), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Reminiscences: Transcriptions, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Book: Joseph W. Hale: Baylor in Perspective (1 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Book: Joseph W. Hale: Baylor in Perspective (2 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Book: Joseph W. Hale: Baylor in Perspective (3 of 3), undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Book: Thomas E. Turner: Robert Emmett Bledsoe Baylor: His Early Years in Kentucky, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Book page, undated (Box [1001], Folder 1)
  - Judge Baylor Family Geneology, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)